Finding Aid for Gunnar Birkerts and Associates, 1960-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- The Calvary Baptist Church, Detroit, Michigan 1974-1987, 344 drawings; 2 linear feet
  - The Calvary Baptist Church Drawings
    - Schematic Design Drawings
      - Preliminary Sanctuary Studies. Pencil and red and blue ink drawings on tracing paper
        - Double Mirror Reflection Study. 05/21/1974 (Map-case 21, Folder 2)
        - Baptistry Mirror as Hinged Portion of Long Mirror. 5/25/7 (Map-case 21, Folder 2)
      - Miscellaneous Plans, Elevations and Details, untitled. Eight pencil and black and brown ink drawings and sketches on tracing paper undated (Map-case 21, Folder 2)
      - Sections, untitled. Ten pencil, black marker and gray wash drawings on tracing paper undated (Map-case 21, Folder 2)
      - [Site Plan], untitled. Pencil on vellum drawing 04/09/1974 (Map-case 21, Folder 3)
      - [Sanctuary Floor Plan and Section], untitled. Red pencil drawing and notations on blue-line print 05/29/1974 (Map-case 21, Folder 3)
      - [Sanctuary Isometric], untitled. One pencil on vellum drawing 05/30/1974 and two colored pencil drawings on blue-line prints, undated (Map-case 21, Folder 3)
      - Schemes I and II Floor Plans. Blue-line print 11/14/1974 (Map-case 21, Folder 3)
      - Site Plan of Parcels 15 and 15A, Indicating Required Removal of Existing Streets, Walks and Alleys (SK-20). Pencil on vellum drawing 05/14/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 3)
      - [Site Plans], untitled. Four colored ink and pencil drawings on blue-line prints undated (Map-case 21, Folder 3)
      - [Space Requirements and Relationship Studies], untitled. Three pencil on vellum drawings and one blue-line print with pencil notations undated (Map-case 21, Folder 3)
      - Lower Level [Floor Plan]. Ink on vellum drawing undated (Map-case 21, Folder 3)
      - Sanctuary [Floor Plan]. Ink on vellum drawing undated (Map-case 21, Folder 3)
      - [Floor Plans], untitled. Two drawings undated (Map-case 21, Folder 3)
      - [Alternative Sanctuary Mirror Studies], untitled. Thirteen pencil and colored pencil drawings on vellum and one red pencil drawing on blue-line print undated (Map-case 21, Folder 3)
      - Sun Angles Studies. One pencil and colored pencil drawing on vellum and one blue-line print with colored marker notations undated (Map-case 21, Folder 3)
      - Structural Drawings by Skilling, Helle, Christiansen, Robertson, Consulting Structural Engineers. Pencil and red pencil drawings on sepia prints, except as noted
        - [Upper Floor Framing Plan] (SHCR-1), untitled. 12/03/1974 (Map-case 21, Folder 4)
        - Ground Floor Framing Plan (SK-1). 1/8/75, revised 02/03/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 4)
        - Upper Floor Framing Plan (SK-3). 1/8/75, revised 02/03/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 4)
        - Sections and Details (SK-4). 1/8/75, revised 02/03/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 4)
        - Partial West Elevation (SK-5). Black-line print 03/10/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 4)
        - Basement, Ground Floor and Upper Floor Framing Plans (SK-6). 03/17/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 4)
        - Work Points and Related Dimensions (SK-7). Blue-line print 03/20/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 4)
        - Basement, Ground Floor and Upper Floor Framing Plans (S1-01). Three prints marked "void," 03/21/1975, 03/28/1975, 04/11/1975 and one print, 04/18/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 4)
        - Roof and Organ Chamber Framing Plans (S1-02). Two prints marked "void," 03/28/1975, 04/11/1975 and one print, 04/18/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 4)
        - North, East and West Elevations and Cross-Section Through Choir and Organ Chamber (S1-03). Two prints marked "void," 03/28/1975, 04/11/1975 and one print, 04/18/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 4)
    - Design Development Drawings
      - Pencil and ink drawings on tracing paper, except as noted undated
        - Elevation B. Two drawings (Map-case 21, Folder 5)
        - Alternate Nursery Elevation (Map-case 21, Folder 5)
        - Proposed Section Looking at Baptistry Dressing Rooms and Exit Door (A) (Map-case 21, Folder 5)
        - Proposed Section Looking at Music Room and Exit Door (A) (Map-case 21, Folder 5)
        - Alternate Stair Section (Map-case 21, Folder 5)
        - Section X-X, Required Stair (Map-case 21, Folder 5)
        - Mirror Dimensions. Red ink on graph paper (Map-case 21, Folder 5)
        - Stair Section at Truss (Map-case 21, Folder 5)
        - Glass Line Relocation Study (Map-case 21, Folder 5)
        - Minister's Toilet Plan and Elevation (Map-case 21, Folder 5)
        - Nave Entrance Door Frame Details (Map-case 21, Folder 5)
        - Floor Drain Detail at Pool (Map-case 21, Folder 5)
        - Pool Details (Map-case 21, Folder 5)
        - [Miscellaneous Plans, Elevations, Sections and Details], untitled. Twelve drawings (Map-case 21, Folder 5)
      - Pencil on vellum drawings, except as noted undated
        - Site Plan. Ink drawing on blue-line print (Map-case 21, Folder 6)
        - Sections at Columns 3 and 8a. Two pencil drawings on reverse sepia prints (Map-case 21, Folder 6)
        - Building Section and Drawing (SK-7). Set of three blue-line prints and one reverse sepia print with pencil notations (Map-case 21, Folder 6)
        - Details #1, 4, 4A and 5 to 12. Seven drawings (Map-case 21, Folder 6)
        - Miscellaneous Floor Plans, untitled. Seven pencil on vellum drawings and one blue-line print with pencil and ink notations (Map-case 21, Folder 6)
        - [West Elevation], untitled (Map-case 21, Folder 6)
        - [Miscellaneous Sections], untitled. Two pencil and orange pencil drawings on vellum; one pencil and orange pencil drawing on reverse sepia print; and four pencil and black ink drawings on blue-line prints (Map-case 21, Folder 6)
        - [Miscellaneous Drawings], untitled. Seven drawings (Map-case 21, Folder 6)
      - Pencil and colored pencil drawings on vellum, except as noted, dated
        - [Site Plan Studies], untitled. Six pencil drawings on reverse sepia prints, 6/14/74-7/5/74, one undated (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
        - [First Floor Plan and Section], untitled. 08/16/1974 (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
        - [Floor Plans, Elevation and Sections], untitled. 09/26/1974 (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
        - [Organ Electrical Layout], untitled, by Bill Hayes. Pencil and red pencil drawing on tracing paper 10/30/1974 (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
        - Construction Sign Elevation. Blue-line print 12/19/1974 (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
        - Upper Floor, Ground Floor, Mechanical Room and Organ Chamber Plans (A-2). Pencil and red pencil drawings on reverse sepia prints, marked "void," revised 01/03/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
        - Upper Floor, Ground Floor, Mechanical Room and Organ Chamber Plans, "sent to Mrs. Applegate, 2/4/75." Blue-line print with red pencil notations 01/28/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
        - South, East, North and West Elevations (A-6). Drawing marked "void," 01/31/1974 (sic) [1/31/75] (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
        - Sections A-A, B-B, C-C and D-D (A-6). Drawing marked "void," 01/31/1974 (sic) [1/31/75] (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
        - Sections E-E, F-F and G-G (A-7). Drawing marked "void," 01/31/1974 (sic) [1/31/75] (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
        - Construction Sign Elevation. 02/24/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
        - Plans, Elevations, Sections and Perspectives of Organ and Organ Bench. 04/23/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
        - Interior Perspective of the Calvary Baptist Church of Detroit, Looking from the Top of the Monumental Entrance Stair. 06/12/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
        - Isometric Drawing of Ground Floor. 06/12/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
        - Isometric of Entire Building, Showing Upper Floor and Partial Ground Floor. 06/12/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
        - Presentation Drawings. Ink on vellum drawings undated (Map-case 21, Folder 7)
          - Floor Plans, Sections and Isometrics. Seven drawings. undated
      - DP Series
        - [Site Plan] (DP-1), untitled. Two pencil and black ink drawings on reverse sepia prints 10/16/1974, 11/05/1974 (Map-case 21, Folder 8)
        - Master Plan (DP-1A). Black ink and pink pencil drawing on reverse sepia print 11/05/1974 (Map-case 21, Folder 8)
        - Ground Floor and Upper Room Plans (DP-2). One yellow marker drawing on blue-line print 10/22/1974 one pencil and red pencil drawing on vellum, 11/5/74; and one blue-line print with red pencil notations, 11/05/1974 (Map-case 21, Folder 8)
        - Sections A-A, B-B, C-C and D-D and Elevations (DP-3). One blue-line print 10/16/1974 and one pencil and red pencil drawing on vellum, marked "void," 11/05/1974 (Map-case 21, Folder 8)
        - Sections E-E and F-F and Reflected Ceiling Plans (DP-4). Pencil and red pencil drawing on vellum, marked "void," 11/05/1974 (Map-case 21, Folder 8)
    - Construction Documents
      - Architectural Drawings. Pencil on vellum drawings 05/21/1975, 08/05/1975, 10/18/1975
        - Title Page. Black ink printing on vellum undated (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Site Plan (A-1). 05/21/1975 revised, 06/10/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Upper Floor, Ground Floor and Organ Chamber Plans (A-2). 08/05/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Lower Level, First Floor Plans and Organ Chamber Plans (A-2). 10/18/1975 revised, 06/17/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Upper Floor, Ground Floor and Organ Chamber Reflected Ceiling Plans (A-3). 08/05/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Lower Level, First Floor and Organ Chamber Reflected Ceiling Plans (A-3). 10/18/1975 revised, 06/17/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Roof Plan, Elevations of Mirror Support System, Sections and Details (A-4). 8/5/75, revised 03/19/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - North, South, East and West Elevations (A-5). Drawing marked "void," 08/05/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - North, South, East and West Elevations and Composite Exterior Elevation (A-5). 10/18/1975 revised, 03/19/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Building Sections (A-6). 08/05/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - [Building Sections], untitled (A-6). 10/18/1975 revised, 06/10/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Building Sections, Kitchen Elevations, Toilet Plans and Elevations and Dressing Room Elevations (A-7). 8/5/756 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Enlarged Plan of Chancel Area and Kitchen, Plan at Entry/Stair, Sections Through Baptistry and Stair #1, and Locations of Electrical and Mechanical Items (A-7). Undated, revised 06/17/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Miscellaneous Plans (A-8). Drawing marked "void," 08/05/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Miscellaneous Sections (A-8). 8/5/75, revised 06/17/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Miscellaneous Elevations, Sections and Details (A-9). Drawing marked "void," 08/05/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Miscellaneous Sections and Details (A-9). 8/5/75, revised 03/19/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Wall Section at East Wall and Plan Details Along East Wall at Ground Floor and at Clerestory and Vertical Window (A-10). 8/5/75, revised 06/17/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Miscellaneous Sections and Details (A-11). 8/5/75, revised 03/19/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Head, Jamb, Sill and Mullion Details (A-12). 8/5/75, revised 1/2/76. (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Plans and Elevations of Pews, Tables, Lectern and Pulpit (A-13). 8/5/75, revised 01/02/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
        - Head, Jamb and Sill Details (A-15). Drawing marked "void," 08/05/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 9)
      - Structural Drawings by Skilling, Helle, Christiansen, Robertson, Consulting Structural Engineers. Pencil on vellum drawings
        - Ground Floor and First Floor Framing Plans (S1-01). 12/5/75, revised 03/19/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 10)
        - Organ Chamber and Roof Framing Plans (S1-02). 12/30/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 10)
        - North, West and East Elevations and Cross Section Through Choir and Organ Chamber (S1-03). 12/30/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 10)
      - Mechanical/Electrical Drawings by Hoyem Associates, Incorporated, Consulting Mechanical & Electrical Engineers. Pencil on vellum drawings, except as noted
        - Site Plan, Catch Basin Detail and Site Lighting Pole Base Detail (ME-1).11/18/75 revised 03/19/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 10)
        - Lower Level and First Floor Plans, Partial Plans of Toilet Room and Lower Level, and Sink and Dishwasher Waste Piping Diagram (M-2). Pencil drawing on sepia print 11/18/1975 revised, 03/19/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 10)
        - Lower Level, First Floor, Organ Chamber and Mechanical Room HVAC Plans (M-3). Pencil drawing on reverse sepia print 10/18/1975 revised, 06/10/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 10)
        - Baptistry Water Piping Diagram and Domestic Hot Water Heater (M-4). 11/18/1975 revised, 01/02/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 10)
        - Baptistry Piping Details (M-5). 11/18/1975 revised, 01/02/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 10)
        - Miscellaneous Details (M-6). Pencil drawing on electrostatic print on mylar 11/18/1975 revised, 01/02/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 10)
        - Control Panel Diagrams (M-7). 11/18/1975 revised, 01/02/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 10)
        - Mechanicals Schedules (M-8). Pencil drawing on electrostatic print on mylar 11/18/1975 revised, 03/19/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 10)
        - Lower Level, Organ Chamber and First Floor Electrical Plans (E-2). Pencil drawing on reverse sepia print 11/18/1975 revised, 06/10/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 10)
        - Electrical Schedules and Riser Diagrams (E-3). Pencil drawing on reverse sepia print 11/18/1975 revised, 01/02/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 10)
        - Architectural Drawings
          - A-1 to A-8. Eighteen blue-line prints with colored pencil notations (Map-case 21, Folder 11)
          - A-9 to A-16. Sixteen blue-line prints with colored pencil notations (Map-case 21, Folder 12)
        - Structural, Mechanical and Electrical Drawings (S1-01 to S1-03; ME-1 to M-8; and E-2 to E-3). Fifteen blue-line prints with colored pencil notations (Map-case 21, Folder 13)
      - Second Bid Set 08/05/1975
        - Architectural Drawings (A-1 to A-16). Eighteen blue-line prints with colored pencil notations (Map-case 21, Folder 14)
        - Structural, Mechanical and Electrical Drawings (S1-01 to S1-03; ME-1 to M-8; and E-2 to E-3). Thirteen blue-line prints with colored pencil notations (Map-case 21, Folder 15)
      - Revisions and Clarifications (SK Series). Drawings on 81/2x11-inch vellum graph and plain paper, except as noted
        - Relocation of Doors F-01 and F-04 (SK-3). 05/05/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Partial Lower Level Plan (SK-4) by Hoyem Associates, Incorporated, Consulting Engineers. 04/29/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Section Through Electrical Closet at Dimmer Control Panel (SK-7R). 05/13/1976 revised, 02/01/1977 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Tree Well Plan and Details (SK-8). 06/30/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Clarification of Ceiling and Steel Grating at Dressing Room #1 (SK-9R). 07/12/1976 revised, 02/01/1977 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Position of Misaligned North Wall Joists at Top of Parapet Per Field Data by A.Z. Shmina & Sons (SK-10). 09/08/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - East Elevation Misaligned Joists Per Field Survey by A.Z. Shmina (SK-11). 09/10/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - West Elevation Misaligned Joists Per Field Survey by A.Z. Shmina (SK-12). 09/10/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - North Elevation Misaligned Joists Per Field Survey by A.Z. Shmina (SK-13). 09/10/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Joint Pattern at Concrete Entrance Walk (SK-14). 10/01/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - South Wall Joists Fabrication Error (SK-15). Electrostatic print 11/22/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Clarification of Choir Ceiling and BM. Casing at Column 42 (SK-18). 02/01/1977 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Partial North Elevation. Undated (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Ceiling Drop at Nursery. Undated (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Untitled Drawing. Undated (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Organ Floor Anchor Bolts. Pencil drawing on yellow legal pad paper undated (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
      - Revisions Drawings (SK series) Pencil on vellum drawings, except as noted
        - [Drywall Detail] (SK-1), untitled. 03/19/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Diagram of Mirror Viewing Range (SK-1A). Pencil drawing on reverse sepia print 10/20/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Architectural Work Point Locations and Elevations (SK-2A). Pencil drawing on reverse sepia print 10/21/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Reflected Ceiling Plan of Lower Level (SK-5). Pencil drawing on reverse sepia print 05/13/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Pulpit, Lectern and Organ Locations (SK-6). Pencil drawing on reverse sepia print 05/13/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Section and Details at Organ Chamber (SK-16). 12/21/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Partial Reflected Ceiling Plan (SK-17). 05/21/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Plan of Choir Area, Floor Plans at Stair #2, Stair Sections, Carpet Seaming Schematic and Miscellaneous Elevations and Sections (SK-19). 05/13/1977 (Map-case 21, Folder 16)
        - Proposed Cap by Industrial Building Panels, Inc. Pencil drawing on blue-line print 07/22/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 17)
        - Preliminary [HVAC Clarifications], untitled. Pencil and ink drawing on reverse sepia print 10/21/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 17)
        - Alternative Study of Lower Level and First Floor Plans. Pencil drawing on reverse sepia print undated (Map-case 21, Folder 17)
        - West Elevation, Work Points and Related Dimensions (SK-11) by Skilling, Helle, Christiansen, Robertson, Consulting Structural Engineers. Sepia print 10/31/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 17)
        - Site Plan, [Grade Revisions] (A-1). Red ink drawing on blue-line print 11/07/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 17)
        - Section Through Main Truss at 4a and 8a. Pencil on vellum drawing 12/23/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 17)
        - Section at Column Line 3. Pencil on vellum drawing 12/29/1975 (Map-case 21, Folder 17)
        - Cross Section Through Organ Chambers. Pencil on vellum drawing 03/31/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 17)
        - Tone Opening Dimensions by W. A. Hayes, Bodman's Organ Service. Pencil drawing on tracing paper and pencil drawing on blue-line print 04/19/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 17)
        - Deck Modifications for Use of Coriform in Lieu of Glass Filler by A.Z. Shmina & Sons Co. Sepia print 05/05/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 17)
        - Construction Sign Elevation. Pencil and ink on vellum drawing 06/16/1976 (Map-case 21, Folder 17)
        - First Floor and Organ Chamber Plans, Reflected Ceiling Plans, Building Sections and Miscellaneous Elevations (A-2, A-3, A-6 and A-13). Set of six colored marker drawings on blue-line prints 1/2/76-6/17/76 (Map-case 21, Folder 17)
        - [Underground Systems As-Builts] (ME-1 and M-2), untitled. Two pencil drawings on reverse sepia prints 01/07/1977 (Map-case 21, Folder 17)
        - Site Plan and Building Elevations. Pencil on vellum drawing 04/29/1977 (Map-case 21, Folder 17)
- University of Michigan Law Library Addition, Ann Arbor, Michigan 1972-1991, 638 drawings; 7 linear feet
  Mechanical/Electrical Engineer: Joseph R. Loring and Associates, Inc.
  Contractor: J. A. Fredman, Inc.
  Landscape Architect: Sasaki Associates
  Agreement Date: January 6, 1977
  Earliest Dated Drawing: December 3, 1974
  Latest Dated Drawing: August 26, 1981
  In her article, " 'Splendor Beneath the Grass' in Michigan" in Architectural Record (March, 1982), Andrea Oppenheimer Dean states that Gunnar Birkerts' University of Michigan Law Library Addition (7 linear feet, 638 drawings; 1972-1991) "is probably the most esthetically satisfying large underground building to have penetrated American soil." Located in Ann Arbor, Michigan, the 77,000-square-foot, subterranean Law Library Addition, which was designed between 1974 and 1977 and completed in 1981, has won two design awards and has been critically acclaimed in 18 national and international architectural journals. Mr. Birkerts was faced with the challenge of building an addition to the existing 1920s faux-Gothic Legal Research Building without compromising its architecture or context. After considering a number of above-ground schemes which unsatisfactorily filled the valuable open space at the southeastern corner of the Law Quadrangle, Mr. Birkerts' final solution was to sink the new structure three stories underground, thereby implementing ideas which he had developed in his Subterranean Urban Systems Study, funded by the Graham and Rackham Foundations in 1974.
  In the University of Michigan Law Library Addition, Mr. Birkerts demonstrates how his renowned, innovative use of daylight influences his architectural design in a dynamic way. A V-shaped, 160-foot-long light trench wraps around two sides of the old Legal Research Building, bringing daylight to all three levels of the new addition. The three floors are open balcony trays from which law students can readily view the icon Gothic building above. One slanting wall and the base of the light trough are constructed of limestone which reflects and diffuses daylight into the interior depths of the library. The mullions of the bronzed, glass, curtain wall of the trench are sheathed with yard-deep mirrors which keep out the glare of direct sun and add refracting complexity to the images of trees, sky and the Law Quad outside. A second, triangular, glass well at the southeastern corner of the building contributes more light to the student lounge and to the back of the building and esthetically perforates the open lawn space above which has been successfully preserved.
  The University of Michigan Law Library Addition series includes seven linear feet of narrative materials, which chronologically document the evolution of the design and construction of the building, and 638 architectural and engineering drawings, which graphically show the entire architectural process from the "Schematic Design" through the "Design Development" and "Construction Document" phases. The pairing of written materials with the original drawings provides researchers with a complete, in-depth picture of the activities of the Gunnar Birkerts and Associates, as the firm designed and managed the construction of one of the most distinguished buildings of the twentieth century in this country.
  Researchers are encouraged to begin their study of the Law Library Addition by reading the "Architect's Conceptual Statement" within the narrative records and the Architectural Record and A.I.A. Journal articles which follow. These will provide an understanding of Mr. Birkerts' innovative thinking and design solutions in meeting the challenge of constructing a light-infused, underground addition to the beloved Legal Research Building. As with all of his work, the character-defining elements of the architecture often result from his creative response to programmatic problems.
  Also of interest to architectural historians will be the "Correspondence In" from the University of Michigan, 1974-1976, which provides insight into the dialogue among members of the Law School faculty and staff concerning the various above-ground and underground schemes. The "Project Chronology, 1974-1978," also gives an historical perspective on the presentation of above-ground "Schemes A, B, C, and D" and on the final selection of the underground concept in 1976.